<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Measure Twice]]></title>
  <link href="http://staceysern.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://staceysern.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-02T10:22:02-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://staceysern.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Stacey Sern]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Types]]></title>
    <link href="http://staceysern.github.io/blog/2013/08/01/types/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-01T14:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://staceysern.github.io/blog/2013/08/01/types</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Much of the work of documenting the Twisted Mail API has involved searching
through the Python code to determine the types for parameters and return values.
It often involves comparing functions in different classes which inherit from
the same base class or implement the same interface.
In some cases, I&rsquo;ve resorted to looking at unit tests or example code to see
how objects are used.
After a recent experience while tracking down types, I&rsquo;m more convinced than
ever of the value of the API documentation.</p>

<p>I was documenting the alias module, which contains classes for redirecting mail
from one user to another user, to a file, to a process, and to a group of
aliases. The four different alias classes inherit from the base class AliasBase
and implement the interface IAlias, which contains the function
createMessageReceiver.
The class hierarchy looks like this:</p>

<pre>
twisted.mail.alias.AliasBase
    twisted.mail.alias.AddressAlias
    twisted.mail.alias.AliasGroup
    twisted.mail.alias.FileAlias
    twisted.mail.alias.ProcessAlias
</pre>


<p>I was trying to determine the return value of createMessageReceiver.
The return value was clear for three of the four classes because the object
to be returned was created in the return statement.</p>

<pre>
FileAlias -> FileWrapper 
ProcessAlias -> MessageWrapper   
AliasGroup -> MultiWrapper 
</pre>


<p>The objects returned are all message receivers which implement the
smtp.IMessage interface.  They deliver a message to the appropriate place:
a file, a process or a group of message receivers.
It seemed pretty clear that the return value of the createMessageReceiver
function in the IAlias interface should be smtp.IMessage.
However, there was one more class that implemented the interface, AddressAlias,
and the return value from that wasn&rsquo;t so clear.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">AddressAlias</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">AliasBase</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">implements</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">IAlias</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">__init__</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">alias</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="n">args</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">AliasBase</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">__init__</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="n">args</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">alias</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">smtp</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">Address</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">alias</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">createMessageReceiver</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">domain</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">exists</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">str</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">alias</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>AddressAlias.createMessageReceiver returns the result of a call to exists on the
result of a call to domain.
Domain is a base class function which returns an object which implements the
IDomain interface.
Fortunately, the IDomain interface was documented.
It returns a callable which takes no arguments and returns an object
implementing IMessage.
Unfortunately, this return value didn&rsquo;t match the pattern of the other three
alias classes.</p>

<p>Although messy, it was possible that the return value of IAlias.createMessage
was either an smtp.IMessage provider or a callable which takes no arguments and
returns an smtp.IMessage provider.
Or, it might have been a mistake.</p>

<p>At this point, I fortuitously happened to be looking at this code in an old
branch and noticed a difference. There, the AddressAlias.createMessageReceiver
function appeared as follows:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">createMessageReceiver</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">domain</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">startMessage</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">str</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">alias</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>After some investigation, I found a
<a href="https://twistedmatrix.com/trac/ticket/4151#4151">ticket</a> that had been fixed
earlier this year to remove calls to the deprecated IDomain.startMessage
function.
In the old code, startMessage also returns an IMessage provider.
So, it seemed that a bug had been introduced in the switch from startMessage
to exists.</p>

<p>The result of the call to exists must be invoked to get the proper message
receiver to return. The code should read:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">createMessageReceiver</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">domain</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">exists</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">User</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">alias</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">)()</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>I filed a <a href="https://twistedmatrix.com/trac/ticket/6638#6638">ticket</a> in the
issue tracking system and subsequently submitted a fix.
While reworking the unit tests, I relied heavily on the API documentation I had
written for the alias module.
I think it&rsquo;s safe to say that had the API been fully documented when the
original change was made, this error would have been easy to spot during code
review or to avoid in the first place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[API Documentation]]></title>
    <link href="http://staceysern.github.io/blog/2013/07/18/api-documentation/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-18T16:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://staceysern.github.io/blog/2013/07/18/api-documentation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My focus for the past few weeks has been on reviewing the API
documentation for Twisted Mail and filling in the missing pieces.
Why bother with documentation when there are bugs to fix and code to write?
The quality of API documentation directly affects the experience that a
developer has employing or further developing a library.
It can be the difference between a piece of software being successfully integrated
into a larger project or being discarded because the user just can&rsquo;t figure out
how
it works.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://twistedmatrix.com/documents/current/api/">Twisted API documentation</a>
is automatically generated from comments embedded in the source code.
The <a href="http://twistedmatrix.com/documents/current/core/development/policy/coding-standard.html">Twisted Coding Standards</a>
dictate that all methods, functions, classes, and modules have docstrings which
describe their purpose and detail all parameters and attributes.
The docstrings are written in
<a href="http://epydoc.sourceforge.net/manual-epytext.html">Epytext Markup Language</a> and are processed
by pydoctor, an API documentation generator, to produce the API documentation.
Epytext provides a way to specify formatting information, to annotate
parameters, return values, and their types, and to create cross-reference links.
Here&rsquo;s an example of a docstring written in Epytext:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">exists</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">address</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">domain</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="sd">&quot;&quot;&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">    Checks whether a user exists in a domain.</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">    @param address: The user</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">    @type address: L{Address}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">    @param domain: The domain</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">    @type domain: L{IDomain}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">    @rtype: C{bool}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">    @return: C{True} if the user exists in the domain, </span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">             C{False} otherwise</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sd">    &quot;&quot;&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And here’s the API documentation that would be generated from that docstring:</p>

<p><img src="http://staceysern.github.io/images/exists.png"></p>

<p>Currently, a good deal of Twisted Mail’s methods, functions, and classes are
missing docstrings. Even those methods and functions that have docstrings
often lack a full description of parameters, return values and their types.
My task is to provide that missing information.  It&rsquo;s a great opportunity to
dive deeply into the code.  And, once the code is fully documented, I&rsquo;ll find
it much easier to fix bugs and introduce new features.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tutorials]]></title>
    <link href="http://staceysern.github.io/blog/2013/06/30/tutorials/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-30T20:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://staceysern.github.io/blog/2013/06/30/tutorials</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If there were a theme for my first two weeks as an Outreach Program for Women
intern, it would be tutorials. As my project, I&rsquo;m maintaining the mail portion
of Twisted, an event-driven, networking framework in Python. I&rsquo;ll be working to
improve the documentation, make progress on partially completed tickets, and
attack some new defect and enhancement tickets. Up until now, I had used several
aspects of Twisted in a project and submitted a couple of patches, but I hadn&rsquo;t
used the mail subproject and wasn&rsquo;t familiar with any of the mail protocols
that Twisted supports. Working through the mail example code and tutorials
seemed like a good introduction and would allow me to evaluate how well the
documentation meets the needs of new users. Further, there were a few
outstanding tickets related to documentation that I&rsquo;d be able to work on
straightaway.</p>

<p>I found immediate success in running the examples of clients that use the
IMAP4 protocol to access email from a remote server. I was also able to run a
simple email server that uses SMTP to receive messages, although I had to read
the source code to figure out from which address it would accept messages. When
it came to the examples of clients which use SMTP to send messages, nothing
worked.</p>

<p>SMTP is a text-based protocol in which a client issues a series of commands and
receives replies from a server in order to send mail. To investigate the
problem with the SMTP client examples, I thought to use telnet to connect
directly to the email server and issue the commands manually. Not only couldn&rsquo;t
I connect with telnet to the servers used in the examples, I couldn&rsquo;t even
connect to a Google server. In all of these cases, I was attempting to connect
on port 25, which is the well-known port for SMTP. My OPW mentor, Jessica
McKellar, theorized that the problem was caused by my ISP blocking outbound
traffic for port 25. Verizon&rsquo;s website confirms that they do this to prevent
virus-infected computers from sending spam.</p>

<p>With this problem in mind, I moved on to the tutorial on how to build SMTP
clients. I ran into the same problem that had earlier prompted a
<a href="http://twistedmatrix.com/trac/ticket/5685">trouble ticket</a>. The
tutorial requires a server running on port 25 of localhost but it does not
explicitly mention this requirement nor does it give directions for running
such a server. A patch had been submitted to explicitly mention the requirement
and suggest that the user could change the example to use an external SMTP
server. A review of that patch had found no problem with the change in wording.
The review, however, raised an ancillary issue, noting that the output listed
in the tutorial did not match what was actually generated by running the
examples. This same complaint was documented in another open
<a href="http://twistedmatrix.com/trac/ticket/6476">ticket</a>.</p>

<p>I wasn&rsquo;t satisfied with the proposed solution, since the user might well be
blocked from contacting an external server on port 25. I thought the best
solution might be to include directions on running a server locally, to be used
with the tutorial. With my limited knowledge of Twisted mail, I modified the
example SMTP server to run on port 25 and accept mail from any user. There were
some quirky requirements involved in running this server, but I was able to get
through the tutorial with it.</p>

<p>Although I had gotten the tutorial working with a local server, I suspected
that my solution might not be the most elegant. Rather than submit a patch and
upon review learn of a better way to solve the problem, I thought it prudent to
consult with the Twisted developer community on the twisted-dev IRC channel. I
learned that I could use the twistd utility to start up a mail server with its
configuration, including the port, specified through command-line flags.</p>

<p>When I mentioned that I planned to update the output listing in the tutorial in
response to both tickets, one developer suggested that was futile since the
output would vary based on release and platform and that it would be better
just to mention in the tutorial that the listing was representative. He then
closed the second ticket, explaining why it wouldn&rsquo;t be fixed.</p>

<p>In the discussion, one of the developers asked me to amend the first ticket to
summarize the problem and specify the completion condition. I specified that
the solution was to make the tutorial self-contained so that a user would need
no external knowledge to work through it. Then I revised the tutorial to make
it so. At the same time, I fixed some issues of formatting, punctuation,
grammar, clarity, and accuracy.</p>

<p>Before I could submit a patch, I needed to build the documentation. Similar to
the process of building code, tools must be run on the raw form of the tutorial
to produce nicely formatted output. Twisted includes a documentation generator
tool called lore which translates XHTML input with annotations to indicate,
among other things, links to API documentation and code listings into HTML
output.</p>

<p>My patch received a quick review. In addition to some requests for minor
changes and clarifications, the review included some comments which seemed to
suggest that the examples used in the the tutorial might not best represent how
to write an SMTP client. I was concerned because the ticket was currently
limited in scope to making the tutorial self-contained. Changing the examples,
while possibly an improvement, would require significantly reworking the
tutorial. In the IRC channel, I asked for confirmation that this was what was
being suggested and if so, should it be done as part of the same ticket. The
consensus was that the suggestion constituted scope creep and should be
addressed in a separate ticket. Now, I am left to submit a few minor revisions
to hopefully close out the ticket.</p>

<p>If that weren&rsquo;t enough in the way of tutorials, I also tackled a new tutorial
on building SMTP servers. Comments had been sitting in the
<a href="http://twistedmatrix.com/trac/ticket/3324">ticket</a> for nine
months. In addition to incorporating the comments, I edited the document and
modified the presentation of some examples to hopefully make them more clear. I
found the final example, which is meant to explain how to use the
IMessageDeliveryFactory interface, to be lacking and wrote a new example to
better showcase it. The changes are nearly ready to be submitted.</p>

<p>Work on these tutorials will continue but my focus is now turning to another
area of documentation &ndash; the API. More on that to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
